Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - McCarty, Perry L., 2014-02-11
    Perry L. McCarty, the Silas Palmer Professor Emeritus of Civil and Environmental Engineering at Stanford University, shares his personal recollections of the choices he made and challenges he faced during his time at Stanford. He discusses his pre-Stanford history and how he was recruited to Stanford to help develop the environmental engineering and science program. He discusses the development and growth of the program with recollections about adding faculty, developing facilities, obtaining grants and contracts, interdisciplinary collaborations, and university politics. He shares his recollections as the chair of the Civil and Environmental Department as well as the creation and growth of the Western Region Hazardous Substance Research Center which he directed. Professor McCarty discusses how Stanford became a leader in creating processes to clean up contaminated groundwater and the impact his research has had on dealing with the development of biological processes for the control of environmental contaminants around the world.
  - Maccoby, Eleanor Emmons, 2011 Feb 16
    In this interview, Eleanor Emmons Maccoby offered great insight into her career in the Psychology Department at Stanford University. Much of the conversation focused on her research into behavior, gender, and linguistic development, from the study of how young children behave to the ways in which language changes based on circumstance and age. She described the Psychology Department’s faculty and administration, as well as the ways in which it has changed over the years. Dr. Maccoby also spoke of the interdisciplinary research efforts that took place on campus during her tenure, and briefly touched on the difficulties faced by female faculty in the middle of the 20th century.
    Born in Tacoma, Washington, in 1917, Eleanor Emmons Maccoby attended Reed College and the University of Washington in Seattle, obtaining her BS from the latter. She earned her MS and Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in experimental psychology, focusing on topics related to the psychology of gender differentiation. Her research has encompassed the socialization of children, developmental change in personality and behavior, relationships of couples after divorce, parent-child interactions, and child-rearing practices. While working at Harvard, she conducted some of the first studies on the impact of television on families and children.
    In 1958, Dr. Maccoby transferred to Stanford, where she became a Professor of developmental psychology and chaired the department from 1973-1976. In 1966, along with Robert Oetzel, Maccoby published her first book on sex-based differences, The Development of Sex Differences. Her most influential book was published in 1974, entitled The Psychology of Sex Differences, co-authored with Carol Jacklin. These publications stressed biological, rather than cultural, influences. Dr. Maccoby has published many books, articles, and papers on her research, and has received awards from the American Psychological Association, the Society for Research in Child Development, and the American Educational Research Association. She is a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1993. Division 7 of the American Psychological Association offers The Maccoby Award to the author of a book making contributions to developmental psychology.
  - Macovski, Albert, 2016-02-02
    Albert Macovski, the Canon USA Professor of Engineering, Emeritus has been affiliated with Stanford since 1960, first as a research engineer and staff scientist at the Stanford Research Institute (SRI) and then as a faculty member with expertise in medical imaging and a joint appointment in the Department of Electrical Engineering and the Department of Radiology.
    In this oral history, Macovski talks about his family background and growing up in New York City in the 1930s. Among other things, he describes his father’s work as a jeweler, the impact of the Great Depression on his family, attending the New York World’s Fair, and his interest in ham radio.
    Macovski recalls his studies in electrical engineering at City College of New York during the immediate post-war period and the significant change in his life occasioned by meeting his future wife, Adelaide “Addie” Paris. He describes obtaining a job at RCA Laboratories upon graduating from college and what it was like to work in the early television industry, including trying to solve problems related to synchronization and color television broadcasting.
    Macovski talks about pursuing his master’s degrees at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn and then working as an assistant professor there. He relates the factors that influenced his decision to accept a job at SRI: a desire to get his PhD, wanting to be where the action in electronics was, and the favorable climate.
    Describing the environment at SRI in the 1960s, Macovski discusses his work on the Nimbus weather satellite and his invention of the single tube color camera. He describes the process of earning his PhD through Stanford’s Honors Coop Program, his dissertation on holography, and a post-doctoral fellowship from the National Institutes of Health that allowed him to study in the Department of Radiology at the University of California San Francisco. He goes on to describe joining the faculty at Stanford and his varied research projects, including work on ultrasonic array, recording images of the beating heart, and developing techniques to differentiate between hard and soft tissue. He also discusses a project to image the coronary arteries. Macovski recounts the story of how a sabbatical year offered him the chance to study magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and to work with Godfrey Hounsfield at the Medical Physics Department of Hammersmith Hospital. He describes obtaining an MRI system from General Electric and the process of getting it installed on campus.
    Macovksi also discusses his approach to working with graduate students and offers reflections on the process of commercializing technology and obtaining patents. He concludes the interview with comments on new directions in the field of medical imaging and on his decision to endow a chair in the Electrical Engineering Department.
  - McDevitt, Hugh O., 2015-07-23
    Hugh O. McDevitt is Professor of Microbiology and Immunology and of Medicine, Emeritus known for his work on major histocompatibility complex (MHC) and its role in various autoimmune diseases. McDevitt discusses his critical research in proving the genetic basis for our bodies’ ability to recognize and defend against pathogens, both from a scientific and personal perspective.
    He begins the interview by describing his early life and how his father, a surgeon, influenced his decision to pursue medicine. He discusses his undergraduate career in the late 1940s at Stanford University, described by others as a “good solid provincial university,” and his undergraduate work in Raymond Barrett’s genetics lab where he mapped the location of a fungus gene involved in metabolism. While the results of this research were not groundbreaking, he stresses the importance of this technique to his later immunology research. Beyond his academic experiences, he speaks about his student life, the jobs he took to help cover his tuition and board, and the death of his father.
    McDevitt goes on to discuss his medical education and training at Harvard Medical School, his internship at Bellevue Hospital in New York—during which he rode the “home care ambulance” all over the city—and his military service in Japan. He recounts his research in Albert Coons’s lab at Harvard and his decision to come to Stanford School of Medicine as a faculty member in the Department of Immunology and Microbiology.
    McDevitt explains how, prior to Stanford, he had observed a difference in the immune system’s reaction to a synthetic peptide between two mice strains. He goes into detail about how, at Stanford, he took a genetic approach to solving this problem and, through selective and extensive breeding, was able to identify the genes (later called the major histocompatibility complex) responsible for the strains’ different reactions. McDevitt gives a technical account of this research, the technical constraints of the day, and the research’s effects.
    He goes on to talk about setting up and running his lab and his experiences teaching, practicing medicine, and chairing his department. At the end of the interview he gives his perspective of how Stanford changed from a “solid provincial regional university” to a “first-class university.”
  - Mark, James B. D., 2015-09-14
    James B. D. Mark discusses his childhood and early influences in choosing his medical profession. He discusses how he was recruited to the Stanford Medical School and the departments in which he served. He was Acting Chairman of the Department of Surgery in 1974 and in 1988 became the Chief of Staff of Stanford University Hospital. He talks about the move of the hospital form San Francisco to the Palo Alto campus, and the relationship between the hospital administration and the medical faculty. He discusses the changes in the field of surgery and the medical student population. He also shares his thoughts on academic medicine and on the current state of primary care in the United States.
  - Merigan, Thomas C., 2015-02
    Thomas Merigan discusses his upbringing and education in the San Francisco Bay Area (Berkeley and UCSF) and his practice in infectious disease at Stanford, which spanned 45 years, including many years as chair of the infectious disease department. He introduced the use of human interferon into the United States in the late 1970s as a treatment for viral diseases. He was also involved in interferon trials for treatment of cancer and multiple sclerosis. Merigan later became an expert in HIV/AIDS, taking care of patients at a time when the options were few. He saw many patients die of the disease. He founded the Center for AIDS Research and the AIDS Clinical Trial Unit, which was involved in testing of a number of promising new treatment options. These drugs became the mainstay of AIDS treatment at the time. Merigan also testified before Congress on the need for science funding. Merigan discussed his most famous patient – Pope John Paul II. He was called in to treat the Pope following an assassination attempt in 1981.
  - Miller, Arjay R., 2012 Apr 11
    In the interview, Arjay Miller recalled his childhood growing up on a family farm near Shelby, Nebraska, and talked about his family history and origin of the family name. He described his life on the family farm with his seven siblings and all of their experiences and adventures, including games they played, songs they sang, toys they made, favorite foods, crops they raised, self-sufficiency and even a few close calls. In addition, he described the local community (churches, social events and schools) and the influences that farm life and growing up during the Depression had on him. He discussed the values he was given by his parents, including finding out how things work, making the most of what you have, and the love of reading and gardening. He covered books he read and radio programs, songs, and newspapers of the day. The interview included many stories and anecdotes that he told as a legacy for his great-grandchildren.
    Arjay Miller was born in Shelby, Nebraska, in 1916 and earned a Bachelor of Science degree from UCLA in 1937. After working as a part-time teaching assistant at UCLA, he worked as an economist for the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco. He then served in the U. S. Air Force before joining Ford Motor Company in 1946 as part of a group of young military veterans who became known as the “Whiz Kids” for their role in retooling the auto giant’s business operations following World War II. He remained at Ford until he accepted the position of Dean of the Stanford Graduate School of Business in 1969.
    Dean Miller served as the fourth Dean of the Stanford Graduate School of Business (1969-1979). Under his leadership, the School rose to the top ranks of management education institutions, expanded its endowment and created the Public Management Program. It was his experiences while at Ford, including communications with government regulators of the auto industry and failed efforts to bring jobs to the inner city in Detroit, that were the foundation for establishing the Public Management Program at Stanford. Through the program, Dean Miller sought to educate students in the concerns of government and society, and government in the needs of business. Within five years, the Stanford Graduate School of Business was voted the number one business school in the country. He was quoted in 1969 as saying, “The problems facing our society today are what I call public goods.”
    The Dean was characterized as a serious, practical, and goal-oriented dean, but he was far from stiff. He enjoyed meeting with young MBAs. There was even a beer-drinking club dubbed the “Friends of Arjay Miller” – FOAM. Under Dean Miller’s leadership, student and faculty diversity in the GSB increased, with the number of African American students increasing from five to 24, Hispanics from zero to 34, and Asian American from four to 27.
    In his tenure at Stanford, Arjay Miller was able to bring the lessons learned from private industry and create an environment for not only academic excellence, but also an awareness of and ability to influence the business world and government for the public good. Arjay Miller is Dean Emeritus of the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University. He is also an Honorary Trustee at The Brookings Institution.
  - Miller, William F., 2009 Jul 10-Aug 5
    Dr. William F. Miller has spent about half of his professional life in business and about half in academia. Dr. Miller came to Silicon Valley from a position as Director of the Applied Mathematics Division at the Argonne National Laboratory where he worked after receiving his PhD in Physics from Purdue University in 1956.At the Argonne National Laboratory Dr. Miller conducted research in basic atomic physics and in computer science. He and his colleagues began early work in what is now called computational science.
    Dr. Miller was the last faculty member recruited to Stanford University by the legendary Frederick Terman who was then Vice President and Provost of Stanford. He was recruited to help form the Computer Science Department at Stanford and to direct the Computation Group at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC). He led the computerization of SLAC and later as Associate Provost for Computing he led the computerization of the Stanford campus. He carried out research in computer science and computer systems and directed the research of many graduate students. As Vice President for Research and later as Vice President and Provost Miller championed the establishment of the Office of Technology Licensing which has become the model for such activities at other universities here and abroad .He actively facilitated the establishment of a number of interdisciplinary programs such as the Human Biology Program, the International Security and Arms Control Program, and the Values Technology and Society Program. In 1978 he negotiated and brought to Stanford the first students from the Peoples Republic of China. In 1979 he was named the Herbert Hoover Professor of Public and Private Management at the Graduate School of Business.
    In 1968 Dr. Miller also played a role in the founding of the first Mayfield Fund (venture capital) as a special limited partner and advisor to the general partners.
    As President and CEO of SRI International Miller opened SRI to the Pacific region, he established the spin-out and commercialization program at SRI and established the David Sarnoff Research Center (now the Sarnoff Corporation) as a for-profit subsidiary of SRI. He became the Chairman and CEO of the David Sarnoff Research Center.
    In 1997 at the 10th anniversary of the founding of the David Sarnoff Research Center, Dr. Miller along with Jack Welsh, Myron DuBain, and James Tietjen received the Sarnoff Founders Medal.
    In 1982 Miller was appointed to the National Science Board; additionally he served on the Computer Science and Telecommunications Board of the National Research Council. He has served on the board of directors of several major companies such as Signetics, Fireman’s Fund America, Wells Fargo Bank, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, Varian Associates, and Borland Software Corp.
    In 1990 Dr. Miller retired from SRI International and returned to Stanford half time where he taught technology-related courses, carried out research on the IT industry and on the characteristics of entrepreneurial regions. He also spent about half of his time working with start-ups and non-profits in Silicon Valley. He helped organize Joint Venture Silicon Valley Network and served on the board of directors for three years. He co-founded and served as Vice Chairman of SmartValley, Inc. Additionally he aided the formation of CommerceNet and served on the board of directors. Dr. Miller was a founding director and served as Vice Chairman of the Center for Excellence in Nonprofits, and was a Founding Member and Chair of the Campaign Cabinet (1992-1994) of the Alexis de Tocqueville Society of Santa Clara. He currently (in 2010) serves as Chairman of the Board of Sentius Corp, Nanostellar, Inc., and Lumiette, Inc. and is a Partner in Actium Ventures (Venture Capital).
    Dr. Miller co-directs an international research project called the Stanford Program on Regions of Innovation and Entrepreneurship and he co-directs an Executive Education program on Strategic Uses of Information Technology.
    Additionally, Dr. Miller worked with foreign countries helping them establish their technology policies and practices, notably Singapore, Malaysia, Japan, and Korea. He served on the International Panel of the Singapore Science and Technology Board, and currently serves on the International Advisory Panel for the Multimedia Super Corridor in Malaysia.
    Dr Miller has received a number of awards and honors:
    Life Member of the National Academy of Engineering, 1987 Life Fellow IEEE, 1999 Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Science, 1980 Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1987 Stanford Computing Pioneer by the AFIPS History of Computing Committee, 1987 Frederic B. Whitman Award, United Way of the Bay Area, 1982 Technology 100 (International Technology Leaders), Technology Magazine, 1981 Tau Beta Pi Eminent Engineer, 1989 Sarnoff Founders Medal, 1997 David Packard Civic Entrepreneur Team Award 1998 Robert K. Jaedicke Silver Apple Award (Stanford Business School Alumni), 1998 The Order of Civil Merit (Dongbaeg Medal) by the Republic of Korea, 2000 The Okawa Prize 2000, The Okawa Foundation, Tokyo, Japan The Silicon Valley Engineering Hall of Fame, 2001 Junior Achievement Business Hall of Fame, 2002 Commendation for Service, Japan External Trade Organization (JETRO), 2002 “Most Mentoring Angel” Award, International Angel Investors, 2002 Honorary Professor, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou China, 2004 Lifetime Achievement Award, Borland Software Corp, 2005 Trustee/ Charter member, Asian American Multitechnology Association, 2007 David Packard Civic Entrepreneur Award, 2008 New Silk Road Award, California Asia Business Council, 2008 Konkuk University, Seoul Korea, establishes the “William F. Miller School of Management of Technology”, March 3, 2009. Miller becomes Honorary Dean
    Dr Miller received the BS (1949), MS (1951), PhD (1956) and Honorary DSC (1972) from Purdue University.
    Dr Miller works with the Cheetah Conservation Fund Namibia which is dedicated to preserving cheetahs in the wild in Namibia. He is a member of the Advisory Board of the Wildlife Conservation Network.
  - Milton, Catherine H., 2014-05-06
    Catherine Milton begins by describing her career trajectory in Washington, DC. She continues with how she met Stanford president Donald Kennedy in Washington and her subsequent recruitment to Stanford as Special Assistant to the President for Public Policy. She describes her efforts in that role, including the formation of Stanford in Washington and the formation of the Haas Center for Public Service. She explains how her experiences and professional contacts in Washington benefitted her work at Stanford, and later how her experiences and relationships at Stanford influenced her in other public service endeavors outside Stanford, such as AmeriCorps.
  - Miner, Anne S., 2014-06
    Anne S. Miner, a professor emeritus known for her research on management and organizational learning, worked at Stanford University in the 1970s as a consultant to the president on affirmative action for women and as the university’s affirmative action officer. She is recognized for her work in designing and implementing the hiring policies and practices related to under-represented minorities. This oral history focuses on the employment status of women faculty at Stanford and, to some extent, throughout academia from the 1970s to the present.
    The first interview session revolve around Miner’s early life and education, her first job at Stanford in the Development Office, her involvement in the burgeoning “women’s movement,” and her work as consultant to the Stanford president on affirmative action for women in 1971. She discusses policy issues that affected women faculty and the formation of the Women’s Forum and the Committee on the Education and Employment of Women.
    In the first and second interview sessions, Miner talks about her role as consultant to the president and the issues she handled, including Stanford’s policies regarding married couples’ faculty appointments, maternity and paternity leaves, the “tenure clock” as it affected women, and part-time employment of faculty. She also discusses the government regulations being passed in the 1970s that required affirmative action programs for all federal contractors and the pressure these regulations put on American universities.
    Miner details issues such as salary equity for staff; training programs for faculty and staff to increase awareness of affirmative action requirements and procedures; child care needs, policies and practices; her role in ensuring that academic searches included women and minorities; and the creation of the Stanford Center for Research on Women in 1974 (now the Michelle R. Clayman Institute for Gender Research). Miner then recalls her decision to leave her job in order to pursue doctoral study at the Stanford Graduate School of Business, her life as a female student with a small child, and the impact affirmative action had on her life as a student.
    In the third and final interview session, Miner discusses her job as a professor of business at the University of Wisconsin and her primary focus and impact in the field of organizational behavior. Looking back, Miner reflects on how her Stanford experience in affirmative action has impacted the rest of her career. She also reflects on the progress women have, and have not, made over the past forty-three years, as well as the issues that still remain. As the interview concludes, Miner offers advice to young women embarking on their academic careers today.
  - Moulton, Robert Harrison, 2007 Apr 2